<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a gentleman to his friend in London in confutation of the scurrilous libell of an anonymus [sic] blackloist [sic], against the reverend and learned P.R. up the occasion of his Latine epistle of the clergie's obedience to the sea apostolick. With an inclosed to the libeller himself.</title>
            <author>T. R.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R86</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217716</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829365</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829365</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33803</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58453)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33803)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1978:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a gentleman to his friend in London in confutation of the scurrilous libell of an anonymus [sic] blackloist [sic], against the reverend and learned P.R. up the occasion of his Latine epistle of the clergie's obedience to the sea apostolick. With an inclosed to the libeller himself.</title>
                  <author>T. R.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on p. 50: T.R.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Pugh, Robert. De retinenda cleri Anglicani in sedem Apostolicam observantia. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Title page is torn, slightly affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pugh, Robert, 1609-1679. --  Retinenda cleri Anglicani in sedem Apostolicam observantia --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33803:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER From a Gentleman to his Friend in <hi>London,</hi> In Confutation of the ſcurrilous Libell of an Anonymus Blackloiſt, Againſt the Reverend and Learned Doctor <hi>P. R.</hi> upon the occaſion of his Latine Epiſtle of the Clergie's Obedience to the Sea A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick.</p>
            <p>With an incloſed to the Libeller himſelf.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Induantur qui detrahunt</hi> [illi] <hi>pudore, &amp; operiantur ſicut diploide confuſione ſuâ,</hi> 
               <bibl>Pſalm. 108.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:33803:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33803:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ter from a Gentleman to his friend in <hi>London,</hi> in Confutation of the ſcurrilous Libel of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonymus Blackloiſt, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THough I cannot chuſe but thankefully acknowledge the great benefit I receive by that friendly correſpondence and good Intelligence you are pleaſed in your weekly Letters to afford me: which by a prompt endeavour of ſerving you, it ſhall be my ſtudy to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve: yet give me leave to chide you a little for your laſt,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33803:3"/>ſince it bore no other mark of Friendſhip but your Name, which I ever eſteemed too ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred to accompany ſo froathy a Libell, ſtuft onely with <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingſgate</hi> Language, too dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bought at Six pence for the Poaſtage, and an hour's read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But ſince the Author is aſhamed to own this ſpurious Bratt, which for want of known Parents wanders a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to beg the ſometimes miſtaken Charity of well-min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded perſons, I ſhall take the boldneſſe to ſend it back to the ſuppoſed place of its birth: But leſt it might finde enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment beyond its deſert,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33803:3"/>and ſo ſteal the Bread due to the Children of the Bride, I have in lieu of a Paſſe-port given it this enſuing Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter and Animadverſion.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="enclosure">
                        <head>To the Libeller himſelf.</head>
                        <p>AS 'tis the greateſt teſtimony of vertue to pleaſe good men, ſo it is no leſs an argument of the ſame to diſpleaſe the wicked; it being equally a blemiſh to be praiſed by them, as to be cenſured by the other: which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the worthy Dr. <hi>P. R.</hi> not onely to ſleight your calumnies, but even made him rejoyce to have received them from ſuch, whoſe Rump-like Anarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chall ſpirits, kick againſt all Authority not modell'd by themſelves, as incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with their Fanatick Notions: And whoſe evident Apoſtacy from the Church, makes them odious and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable to the genuine Sons thereof:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33803:4"/>and might therefore have driven me and others, friends of the Doctor and Truth, to have paſſed by this Libel with contempt, as confident it will finde the ſame judgement in <hi>England,</hi> which it could not have avoided in a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Countrey, by Tobacconiſts, if it eſcape a more noyſom burial by piece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meal in a Cloſe-ſtool, Yet leſt it might fall into the hands of ſome unacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with his merits and worth; and becauſe Reproaches confidently urged, leave ſome durt behinde them; I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it my duty to wipe it off: a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I owe to Truth, to my deceived Friends, to the Doctors Innocency, whoſe eminent Vertues afford me a large field to wander (and even loſe my ſelf) in, in his commendations, did I not fear to offend his modeſty, and derogate from his juſt merits by my humble Pen, as much below his deſert, as he is above your detractions.</p>
                        <p>But what ſhould move the unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Publiſher of this ſcandalous Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quill to vent to the World ſo ſcurril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Pamphlet, <hi>whoſe Author he knew
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33803:4"/>not, nor the man he writes againſt;</hi> but covetouſneſſe, which legitimates any gain, though by the hurt of others, yea ſcarce thinks it gain, unleſſe others be hurt. A notable wiſe Fellow that could think a Letter worthy the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, whereof <hi>he neither knows the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> whether he be a man who may deſerve belief; <hi>nor the man he writes againſt,</hi> whether his worth may not have heightned him above all ſuch barkings.</p>
                        <p>But whether I ſhould believe him or you, I know not, whom I finde like <hi>Suſanna</hi> her witneſſes, in ſeveral tales; and while your Heads look diverſe wayes, are tyed onely by the Tailes, where in that of your Letter, you ſay, <hi>He knows the hand,</hi> which he in full front denies, <hi>Non novi hominem. Oedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> ſolve me this Riddle, <hi>Know and know not.</hi> But perhaps your Maſter <hi>Blackloe</hi> in his new Philoſophy hath found a cure for it out of the World in the Moon, to which we recommend him, ſince he hath troubled this ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently: And in particular to the Man
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33803:5"/>thereof, who in all likelihood tyred with great imployment, may reſigne his place to him, or at the worſe, make him Reader of Divinity there, ſince all Countries have refuſed him here.</p>
                        <p>'Tis very credible that Dr. <hi>P. R.</hi> his neareſt acquaintance and camerades ſhould ſo ill befriend him, as to give you Mr. Libeller, ſuch a knowledge of him as you blaze out in your ſcurril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Pamphlet. I have the honour to be of his neareſt acquaintance, and (be it ſpoken with the reſpect I owe his perſon and worth) of his Camerades, and out of mine own knowledge will make bold to give you the Lye, and your very Pamphlet ſmells of ſo much baſeneſſe and cowardize, that I believe you will cake it patiently. And I ſhall praiſe your vertue.</p>
                        <p>But much more true, that <hi>you never had any commerce with himſelf,</hi> his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ever diſdaining ſo inconſiderable a Fellow, by whoſe company his repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation might ſuffer in the opinion of men of worth, <hi>his neareſt acquaintance and Camerades.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:33803:5"/>
                        <p>Then you ſay, your <hi>profeſſion hath no relation to the ſubject of this diſcourſe,</hi> I believe ſo; for you not onely ſeem no Schollar, but even not worthy to look at ſchollarſhip, who could ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle diſcern it, where it appeared as ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and gracefully as the matter requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And therefore doubt not but your own confeſſion will eaſily be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, <hi>viz,</hi> That you are neither <hi>a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, nor learned in any thing:</hi> no not ſo much as in good manners, or the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a good Catholick, though you profeſſe your ſelf <hi>a Roman Catholick.</hi> Which whether I may take upon your own word, wherein you have faultred ſo often, and is yet the onely teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall you have, I leave to honeſt men, and ſuch as have read your Pamphlet to judge: till then I ſhall be content out of charity to hope, though I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not finde one word in all your Libell can induce me to believe it.</p>
                        <p>Though I can eaſily credit, and you have demonſtrated it more fully then your Maſters <hi>Chryſaſpis</hi> did the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dratura Circuli,</hi> that you <hi>are neither a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33803:6"/>Divine, nor learned in any thing, onely you pretend</hi> [and but barely pretend] <hi>by common ſenſe</hi> [which any one that reads your Pamphlet would ſwear you had loſt] <hi>bettered with converſation and reading, to have ſome knowledge</hi> [but that very little] <hi>of the ordinary paſſages of the world, and in ſuch matters as men generally talk of:</hi> which whether any Tinker, Cobler, or ſweep-chimney, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in theſe times ſo full of news and buſineſſe, may not more then <hi>pretend to,</hi> I wiſh you out of <hi>your common ſenſe bettered with converſation and reading</hi> [your Maſters Books] to determine.</p>
                        <p>You do well not to be <hi>of the opinion</hi> of thoſe that think him <hi>hired:</hi> for in that particular, you will be accompted leſſe ſilly then they who think ſo, and vent their venome ſo weakly and groundleſly.</p>
                        <p>You do well alſo <hi>not to believe that he is a Prevaricator,</hi> for no honeſt man would believe you. And if thoſe <hi>others</hi> you ſpeak of, are aſhamed to own that belief before any perſon of honour; I pray you be you aſhamed of them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33803:6"/>and of your acquaintance with them. And I wiſh I could as eaſily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit you of a malicious deſigne in your carriage towards him: that you were not the hireling of ſome Purſevant, whom by this open diſcovery of his Name and Perſon you endeavour to aſſiſt: that by the ruine of ſo worthy and learned an Adverſary, you might leave an open field to your baffled and run-away Champion <hi>Blackloe.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Good Sir begin to read his piece once more, and if you cannot for an example, in the firſt dozen lines or more, ſhow us <hi>that palpable lye, or ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or ſcolding injuſtice, or railing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, or at leaſt ridiculous imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency,</hi> know what a fellow you are that <hi>dares ſay that there are not three lines in the whole piece without ſome of this.</hi> And how guilty will your Reader finde your ſelf of all this; when you begin ſo timely.</p>
                        <p>You ſay <hi>he deſerves not to carry their Books after them.</hi> You ſay right, for we cannot ſee how having ever made the good uſe, we know, of the beſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33803:7"/>Books, why he ſhould be condemned to read ſuch naughty Books as your friend's are: but his zeal for our good makes him read them, to diſcover their venome to us, leſt they might infect us. Beſides, the bulk of your Maſters comes will never (I am ſure) oppreſſe his ſhoulders, whoſe ſtomack accuſtomed to ſolid Learning will eaſily digeſt his Pigge-wiggin Divinity into ſippets.</p>
                        <p>Here again you do the Purſevant a pleaſure. The party you write againſt doth not ſo much to his worſt adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: he names but one, and him by two letters onely. If he names one or two of his friends at length, as you do him, it is with their conſent; I am ſure you had not his conſent to do ſo.</p>
                        <p>Poor man, though you conceal your name, yet leaſt it come out at laſt, why have you no more care of your credit, then to diſcover ſo much ignorance, ſince you profeſſe <hi>to have ſome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the ordinary paſſages of the world,</hi> as to think that a man cannot leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Jeſuit without Apoſtacy. We ſee even Princes, both Temporall and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33803:7"/>Spirituall, Prelates, Doctors, Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and other perſons of eminency and honour, often do it with the world's eſteem, and continuance of mutual cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity betwixt them and the Society. But becauſe you think no ignorance can befall your friend Mr. <hi>White,</hi> from whom you raked this with his other durt, you were the bolder in ſhooting your bolt.</p>
                        <p>Your owne Pamphlet and your friend's Mr. <hi>White</hi>'s gives you the open lye, ſince with the utmoſt of your fury and filthy language you cannot faſten the leaſt blemiſh upon any part of his life, even in the two or three particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar paſſages in matter of fact, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you go about to do it here; he hath ſo fully and ſo openly heretofore cleared himſelf to all your confuſions, that I extreamly wonder how like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Owls out of your Ivie-buſhes you dare flie at a perſon whoſe life hath been ſo open and ſo eſteemed by perſons of all degrees, both higheſt and loweſt. For the ſatisfaction of thoſe who know him not, I ſhall anon take
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33803:8"/>notice of your two or three fabulous calumnies.</p>
                        <p>Beſides the baldneſſe of your ſtile all over, I take notice that all your ſlanderous Epithers and Adverbs, run along barking in couples: as <hi>notorious and foul reproaches, baſely and unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſeth, frivolous and fooliſh Lines, lewd and licencious Pen;</hi> and ſo all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long. But all this will never bite. No not your often calling him <hi>poor wretch,</hi> can no more wrong him, then <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> (with whom you jump in that Reviling Expreſſion, take heed you jump not home after him) did his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Sovereign.</p>
                        <p>How ſimple is your malice here, as if it were a diſparagement to teach thoſe Schools which in courſe both Princes and Prelates, and whoſoever was of that Society, taught: And I pray you, who of your beſt friends did not the like at <hi>Doway?</hi> Though any man that reads the bald expreſſions of your Maſters, <hi>White</hi> and Doctor <hi>H. H.</hi> would never think they had put foot into a Grammer-School, whoſe Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33803:8"/>they are not worthy to read to Boyes.</p>
                        <p>Your fooliſh jearing his Majeſties Army, in calling them <hi>the brave Blades of the Land,</hi> makes it likely, that you are one of thoſe Levelling Coxcombs, who cared not much for that Cauſe, and ſo envied thoſe you durſt not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire to follow, and appear with; this worthy perſon whom you now ſharle at, was a conſtant comfort to the beſt Catholick Nobility and Gentry, with their Officers and Souldiers, with open hazard of life in ſuch encounters, where you my friend, who dare not now own your name, durſt not then ſhew your face: his wounds and impriſonment for that Cauſe, and in the performance of his noble charity, have gotten him that eſteeme you will never deſerve, without your becoming another crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture then you ſeem to be. And that with ſuch ſucceſs, that many Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able perſons in their laſt agony, owe their Reconcilement to him: the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of which duty, argues in your friends as little charity to the dying, as their Doctrine expreſſeth to the dead;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33803:9"/>who inſtead of ſuch Heroick acts of Fortitude, are ſneaking in holes, where they ſtrain all their forces to gain ſome filly woman, whoſe purſe out-weighs her wit, to contribute to the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of their Chimerical Chapter.</p>
                        <p>Your <hi>Ex-Jeſuit</hi> being <hi>caſt out,</hi> and being <hi>a Deſertor,</hi> ſhows your non-ſenſe and contradiction; if <hi>a Deſertor,</hi> which implieth freely parting, how <hi>caſt out,</hi> or forced to depart?</p>
                        <p>The <hi>twang</hi> they retain (if you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood what you ſay) is their eſpecial ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to the Pope, and zeal againſt Hereſies and profane Novelties, which they were particularly bred to in the Society: which with their indefatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble charity, hath carried them through ſo many dangers both by ſea and land, to the Converſion of millions of Souls in both the <hi>Indies;</hi> whilſt your party in the mean time imitating the incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible malice of ſome of thoſe barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous people againſt the Spaniards, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe Heaven, becauſe you are ſure to finde Jeſuits there: and to that end uſe all your wiles to pervert thoſe ſouls, whom they with other Clergie Secular
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33803:9"/>and Regular, have with ſo great pains gained to God.</p>
                        <p>You ſay <hi>the world takes,</hi> &amp;c. You mean the ſenſleſs world, whereof you are one, and in this alſo chuſe rather to run blind after your Maſter <hi>White,</hi> then to inform your ſelf of thoſe who could have told you; and you might clearly have gathered as much out of ſundry places of the Epiſtle it ſelf, which no way agree to the worthy Lord Abbot you name, that the perſon meant by <hi>M. G.</hi> is a vertuous and learned Cleargy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in Monmouthſhire. And your apiſh following of <hi>Blackloe</hi> in his very mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes, how ſimple ſoever, makes you call the Author <hi>Monumetham;</hi> which you that talk ſo much of Grammer and Pedantry, if you read but <hi>Manutius</hi>'s Letters ſhould have known, where you finde the names of the places whither the Letters are ſent. As for that illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious worthy Prelate on whom you would needs ground your ſillymiſtake; all your ſlanders and back-bitings will not leſſen his affection to this worthy perſon, and his ever owning his former ſervices, as I and many more can ſtill
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33803:10"/>witneſs the conſtancy of this perſons profeſſions of zeal for his ſaid Patrons ſervice. And moreover, know my ſilly friend, that your Informer's too much ſnott ſtops their noſtrils, and their breath ſtinks if they are not ſenſible of the ſweet odour ſtill remaining of his exemplar and obliging comportment at <hi>Pontoiſe.</hi> The beſt and greateſt there will teſtifie it, as I dare undertake, to the confuſion of any that ſhall dare to appear in this ſlander. And here I muſt tell you, you ſtumble againſt your will at an honour this deſerving perſon was thought worthy of, which neither your Dr. <hi>H. H.</hi> nor your Maſter the Trino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant ever yet obtained, for what I hear, in any forreign parts, to wit, to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted by the King of <hi>France,</hi> under the great Seal, with the adminiſtration and government of a Royal Abbey, with all its dependencies, to wit, above forty Churches; a truſt uſually judged there too great to continue in the ſame hands above ſix moneths without new Paterts; and in him was continued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove two yeares, in teſtimony of his prudent and knowing mannagement,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33803:10"/>that is to ſay, all the time the Abbey remained in vacancy.</p>
                        <p>Then you ſo tumble and delight your ſelf <hi>in excrements noyſome and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted members, ill ſents</hi> and ſuch like perfumes, that I doubt not but your ſagacious noſe may well befit a Town-Sow.</p>
                        <p>And now my Dr. Dullman, let me once for all take notice, that however <hi>you pretend by common ſenſe bettered with converſation and reading to have ſome knowledge,</hi> yet that 'tis very little, and your wit leſs, which for want of better matter hath forced you to harp ſo often on the ſame ſtring, of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors <hi>teaching of a Grammer School:</hi> from whence it ſeems you are but late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clapſed; and the marks of your ignorance on your Poſteriors have made ſuch a fearful impreſſion on your memory, it ſcarce retains any other Idea but of that formidable bug-bear wherewith it thinks to terrifie others: But we <hi>manum ferulae ſubduximus.</hi> And therefore let me tell you, for you are not able to judge your ſelf, that Dr. <hi>P. R</hi>'s knowledge in all Literature
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33803:11"/>both Divine and Humane, is ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, his ſtile in Verſe and Proſe ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite and terſe, that the truth thereof more forcible then any rack, hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted this confeſſion from your Mr. <hi>White,</hi> a man otherwiſe ſparing in his Praiſes: who in his <hi>Mon. excant. pag.</hi> 5. ſaith. <hi>Candide agnoſco; nam &amp; ſcriptum tuum Latinè terſum eſt, neque verboſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatè diffluis; &amp; dignus es cujus ſtylo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colatur veritas; &amp; vidi aliquando ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiculos à te profectos, qui lucem non ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerentur.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Afterwards, like him that would make Wind-mills on <hi>Salisbury</hi> Plains, to drain the Fennes, you ſhew your Aſſe's ears in going about, to excuſe <hi>the Catholick Engliſh Cleargy</hi> from par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking in the guilt of Dr. <hi>H. H's</hi> Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, touching the reading of prohibited Books, (a book as deſtructive of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, as the <hi>Corolarium of his Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſis</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> of Civill Authority) I pray you who ever accuſed them? or once thought them guilty of ſuch a crime, which they equally abhorre with your Maſters Novelties: You might have ſaved this breath to cool your pottage.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33803:11"/>And then loudly bellow, <hi>Dr. P. R. was reſolved to throw an aſperſion on the Cleargie;</hi> a falſe ſlander, and ſuch for which in conſcience (if you had any) you owe him a reparation: ſince all along he gives them thoſe Encomiums ſuch venerable Brethren might deſerve and expect from the eloquent Pen of an affectionate Brother: 'Tis you and you Maſters the trumpetters of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties he juſtly ſtrikes at; from ſuch Wolves like a good Paſtor he defends his flock. Was ever Evangeliſt charged as injurious to the Colledge of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles for blazing out <hi>Judas</hi>'s apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? And what manner of Cleargy-men your friends are, the Catholick and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>extorted teſtimony of moſt of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars in <hi>England</hi> (not to mention Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulars, with whom you have no chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but with your father <hi>Luther</hi> cry, <hi>Monachus eſt, ja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>dudum illum valere juſſi</hi>) in deteſtation of your Maſter and his Doctrine, will evidently teſtifie, when it ſhall be required of them.</p>
                        <p>Then you blame him for <hi>praiſing Obedience to the Magiſtrate in generall.</hi> A great fault indeed; and ſuch as with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33803:12"/>you and your Maſters (whoſe ſeditious Writings againſt the Supreme Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Spirituall and Temporall, have made them deſervedly odious to all honeſt men) deſerves reprehenſion and puniſhment.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And that out of Cicero too:</hi> true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: And can your ſteel'd impudence refrain bluſhing to hear <hi>Cicero</hi> a Pagan out-ſtrip you and your Maſters, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Chriſtians and Catholicks, in your duties to God and the King. <hi>Viri Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivite ſurgent in judicio cum generatione iſta, &amp; condemnabunt eam.</hi> Away for ſhame, and diſgrace not Chriſtianity with your unchriſtian-like Doctrine and manners.</p>
                        <p>For the Doctrinall part of that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Epiſtle of Obedience to the Sea Apoſtolick, poor ſcribler, you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply ſo little to the purpoſe to it. that the onely thing I allow of in this rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Libell, is your own confeſſion that you are <hi>neither a Divine, nor learned in any thing.</hi> And you ſhew it here ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently. Neither will I ſo far ſhew my ſelf a Divine, as to foreſtall what I am confident this worthy Author of that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33803:12"/>Epiſtle prepares for your great Maſter the Trinobant himſelf, as I dare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe my ſelf to the world's ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And indeed this fooliſh piece be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtoln from your <hi>Maſtors Excanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> deſerves not to be taken notice of by it ſelf.</p>
                        <p>Onely by the way let me advertize you, that if it ſuffice in anſwer to the Doctors Reaſons, onely to ſay, as you do pag. 4. You <hi>are aſhamed to read them, and ſhould be no leſſe aſhamed to trouble your ſelf ſo far as to anſwer them in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</hi> What Ideot, though as your ſelf <hi>not learned in any thing,</hi> might not thus ſolve thoſe Difficulties all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines and Philoſophers of the world have ſo long time beaten their brains about in vain. But the leſs learning the more preſumption. <hi>None ſo bold as blind Bayard:</hi> This is that compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious way the ignorant Doctor <hi>Tolſon</hi> took to confute the eminent and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine. Bellarmine thou lieſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Then with like confidence and as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reaſon you ſay, (and we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve your <hi>ipſe dixit,</hi> as you do your
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33803:13"/>Maſters <hi>ſtat's, conſtats, certum eſt, &amp;c.</hi> but my name is <hi>Thomas) that no Law whatſoever did obliege the Subject till it were promulgated.</hi> Wherein you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover your ignorance even in our own Parliamentary Laws, which require no promulgation in the ſeveral Shires, but are binding when they have thrice paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Houſes, and obtained the Kings conſent.</p>
                        <p>Then you ſnarle at the Doctor for ſaying, <hi>That the Lawes of particular Prelates do not obliege but by Authority from the Pope, as though their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity were not immediately from Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> How then comes the different Authorities of Patriarchs, Primates, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, &amp;c? were their ſeveral Juriſdictions ſet apart by Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, without the mediate intervention of his Vicars on earth? But what ſpeak I of Authority to you and your Maſter <hi>White,</hi> who contemns all of Pope, Cardinals, Nuncio, his own Biſhop, &amp;c? and will onely bend the knee to the <hi>Baal</hi> of his own Fancy.</p>
                        <p>Then you ſay, <hi>He raileth</hi> (for to call a thief, a thief, with you is railing) <hi>at
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33803:13"/>the Provinciall Letters, at the Janſenian Sect,</hi> which (by inſtinct no doubt, or ſo told by your omniſcient maſter, for you <hi>know him onely by relation</hi>) you are pleaſed to fable <hi>he never underſtood:</hi> Happy <hi>Calvin!</hi> happy <hi>Janſenius!</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py <hi>Blackloe!</hi> had they never taught it; and thrice happy world had it never underſtood it, but left it in Hell, whencetheſe unhappy Maſters have ſo fatally raked it.</p>
                        <p>Next you ſtrive to clear <hi>Dr. H. H. from ſaying theſe Roman Decrees num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam in Galliis recipi: and that he ſaith onely, they are not alwayes admitted, but ſometimes rejected.</hi> Very well! and hath lawful Authority never been rejected? Were the Patriarcks, Prophets, and even Jeſus Chriſt our B. Saviour himſelf always received? were the Apoſtles and their Succeſſors with their Doctrine and Laws welcome in all places? No, and yet nevertheleſs binding. Well argued Dr. and Libeller <hi>à facto ad jus:</hi> And even this <hi>ſometimes refuſall</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds moſt commonly not from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to the decree, but the claſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Spiritual and Temporal Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33803:14"/>in their ſeverall pretences to the right of promulgation.</p>
                        <p>But now the Fox begins to preach, Lambs look to your ſelves, for I muſt take notice of this unknown Libeller's impertinency, who would perſwade us that thoſe who maintain obedience to his Holines his Decrees only <hi>in foro con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiae,</hi> and in ſuch matters, as do no way meddle with the State, are worſe Subjects then thoſe lurkers of his gang who brought a ſcandall upon Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, by their publiſhing and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that deteſtable book of <hi>Obedience and Government,</hi> printed in <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s time, to aſſert his Uſurpation againſt the then diſpoſſeſſed ſupream Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, our Royal Sovereign, whom God grant long to bleſſe us with his happy reign. It is too well known how theſe petty Levellers were content to wait on, and brag of their favour with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee-men, perſwading their friends ſtill to a deſpair of the happineſſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hath now reſtored to us. 'Tis well known to nobler perſons then this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller hath the face to be acquainted with, how the perſon he rails at, by his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33803:14"/>wounds, impriſonment, and many years baniſhment upon his Majeſties ſcore, gave moſt conſtant teſtimonies of his loyalty, and ever moſt zealouſly oblie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thoſe he directed, to the like: let both your Maſter and Doctor take heed the contrary be never laid home to their charge.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Quis tulerit Gracchos de ſeditione que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You ſay <hi>the Dr. will be glad his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is called Harpya,</hi> for you think it was ſo indeed, becauſe it brought you <hi>more light.</hi> I fear you take <hi>Harpya</hi> to ſignifie a Lanthorn. Look in your Dictionary and think whether it was a Beaſt or a Bird that hooked in and caught ſuch fools as you into miſperſwaſion. But we are much beholden (you ſay) <hi>to Dr. H. H. for the light and knowledge of what is truly of obligation in points of Religion, and what not, he affords his countrey-men ſhut up in an Iſland, and thence ſomewhat ignorant of the proceedings of Forreigne nations in relation to Rome.</hi> Very well! you are pleaſed with any thing that tends to diſobedience to the Sea Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick, let it come from <hi>Geneva, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi>
                           <pb n="26" facs="tcp:33803:15"/>yea Hell it ſelf: let it bring with it never ſo great ſcandall to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the profeſſors of it, though it derogate never ſo much from the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Church, the immaculate Spouſe of Chriſt, and thoſe glorious Saints ſhe hath enrolled in the Canon of the Bleſſed: its welcome, and belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as Goſpel. But <hi>if ſome Jeſuit write any thing</hi> (though never ſo good) <hi>from Rome, or Ex-Jeſuit bring it in his pocket:</hi> Then <hi>faenum habet in coru.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You are troubled with <hi>Monume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham's non-ſenſicall Arguments,</hi> he will trouble you no more, he thinks you not worth the pains. And I too.</p>
                        <p>Then you triumph in the condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>the Apology for the Caſuiſts.</hi> And ſo do I. As alſo in that of Janſeniſme, the Provinciall Letters, and <hi>Blacklos's</hi> Books, and receive them equally with open arms; why do not you ſo too? And though you falſly impoſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary on the Jeſuits, and for that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended diſobedience would needs ſhake hands with them, like Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeches that faſten onely where the Blood is corrupted: know they ſcorn
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33803:15"/>you. <hi>Nulla ſocietas luci &amp; tenebris.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>I will ſay nothing of the Dr. you ſo much extoll, I know him not otherwiſe than by his writings, which are weak and ſcandallous. This onely I know, that when better men than you ſhall queſtion it, it will be made good, that the Paſtor of St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> warned him to keep out of his Church, rather then infect any of his Penitents with Janſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, &amp; unwarrantable novelties, which I have from a worthy Divine's owne mouth, to whom the Paſtor himſelf told it; and that the Dr. thereupon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to conform himſelf, was ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to continue. Neither did I ever hear that the Dr. came otherwiſe to St. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas,</hi> then as an extern or ſupernume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary: not as a domeſtick, either Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giate or Seminariſt, as the perſon you foam at had the honour to be a long while at St. <hi>Sulpice,</hi> where his ſingular exemplarity as well in the labours of that miſſion, as the moſt deſperate ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which befell him in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the holy Sacraments to an infected poor creature, was even by the chief of the Engliſh Clergy who often
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33803:16"/>viſited him, acknowledged and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily joyed at, as a credit to his nation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſtrangers. And when his decaſions oblieged him to retire to the Colledge of <hi>Authune,</hi> to ſpend ſome years in the Canon Law, in order to his Doctorate in that faculty, the ſaid worthy Paſtor of St. <hi>Sulpice</hi> at his departing intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, that he would ſtill own himſelf as a member of their miſſion; and gave order there ſhould be a Surpleſs ſtill kept ready for him, when he would pleaſe to come, as he did now and then to help them. Now Sir, where lieth all this while the ground of your lye that <hi>he was infamouſly expelled for ſuch pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and notorious ſcandals as you are aſhamed to name?</hi> I will tell you more than you ſeem to know, not for your own ſake, but becauſe another of your companions (who being of a better tongue and more wit then your ſelf, though of as undiſerect a temper, may be thought rather your Informer then the Author of your Libell) had the face to come with ſome aſperſion in that kinde, though far ſhort of the heighth you raiſe it to, unto a noble perſon, who
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33803:16"/>knowing well with what particulars he might ſoon be confounded, adviſed him for his own credit's ſake to hold his peace. A Lay Gentleman, at this perſon you would aſperſe, his refuſall to pay him ſome money, which he had yet no order to give him, by injurious language provoked him to ſome words of choler, and thereupon alſo made complaint unto the ſaid Paſtor, who for his too haſty crediting the Gentlemans report againſt his brother, became a day or two after ſo ſorry, that of his own accord, inſtead of the teſtimonial commendations he had formerly given him, as the manner was, he would needs beſtow new ones, with an inſerted clauſe importing his having been miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>informed, and that he not onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged him free from the leaſt blemiſh in all his comportment, but moſt worthy of the commendations, he then gave him in writing under his hand. This teſtimony and more yet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame occaſion, will be produced when any worth the ſatisfaction ſhall require it. And all this was ſo farre
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33803:17"/>from an expulſion, as your impudence would perſwade us, that this perſon lived not then at St. <hi>Sulpice,</hi> but went thither onely ſometimes to help them, as he did ſtill a long time after this, at their earneſt requeſt; and being oblie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Paſtor's new civilities, who in teſtimony of his further affection, made his own brother, being the Lord Chancelour of <hi>France</hi> his grand Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encer, procure him the great Seal for his naturalization <hi>gratis,</hi> with an intent to obtain for him ſoon after, as great a Benefice as the limitation of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent for naturalization could admit of. Yea moreover, procured him priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Faculties for extraordinary extent of Juriſdiction over all that Dioceſſe. As that moſt illuſtrious Lord Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Roven,</hi> and Primate of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy,</hi> did afterwards of his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, inviting him thereunto, give him equal faculties to his own Vicar Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. To ſay nothing of the moſt illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Lord <hi>Bayny</hi> his Holineſſe his Nuncio, ſince made Cardinal, his ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him one of his Aſſeſſours to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33803:17"/>the Witneſſes and frame the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatories about the validity of the Duke and Ducheſſe of <hi>Loreine</hi> their Marriage, wherein I hear he laboured with great applauſe and ſatisfaction of the Nuncio. And all this after your pretended notorious ſlander, and he that will dare own his name (which you do not) to the deniall of it, will be proved a notorious lyar.</p>
                        <p>Now having abundantly cleared my friend, I will not go about to charge yours the Doctor, though your offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous over-clawing him puts the world in minde of the reports they have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten heard of him. I have heard the perſon I here vindicate ſpeak civilly enough of your Doctor, neither have I heard him complaine that your Dr. had perſonnally diſoblieged him; one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that his croſſing your Doctor's en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to recommend Blackloiſme to us by ſuch factious Pamphlets, hath hitherto reflected more upon the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and but moderately enough up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the writer. Yet becauſe your indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, for which I believe you will
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33803:18"/>have little thanks from your Doctor, obligeth me to it, I muſt needs tell you, that beſides what I have heard, I have ſeene Letters under another vertuous deſerving Church-man's hands, who was all this while at <hi>Paris,</hi> repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Doctors mannaging of thoſe Almes you mention, farre more to his diſcredit, then you do, both for the manner and the perſons they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon: yea, warning him of blemiſhes more openly ſpoken of, and of a farre worſe Nature than any you have endeavoured to aſperſe my friend with. I will conceale the particulars, until I be called upon to make good what I ſay. But before I leave your Doctor I muſt take notice, that you do not ſo much as offer to clear him of the fickleneſſe and inconſtancy he is by my Author charged with, for his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing in publick to the condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Janſeniſme, to the high diſſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of his owne party, and then owning that Hereſie ſtill in private to regain their good wills: and that in his pittifull Epiſtle thereupon to the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33803:18"/>Paſtor of St. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> he ſo played the John of both ſides, that his Epiſtle and he were commonly hiſſed at. Perhaps you meane this for one, in this place where you are pleaſed to play the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comiaſtes, ſaying, <hi>Thoſe two learned and famous Epiſtles.</hi> As you do alſo in the next leaf on <hi>his Preliminary Epiſtles to his Commentary on the New Teſtament, of which</hi> you <hi>onely ſaw the firſt leaves.</hi> Surely you are miſtaken, it was <hi>his Preface</hi> (which gave him the ſirname of <hi>Dr. Preface</hi>) the Book whereto we have for many years in vain expected; and of which in a Modern Poets words we may ſing,
<q>
                              <l>A Preface to no Book? a Porch to no Houſe?</l>
                              <l>We ſee the Mountain, but where's the Mouſe?</l>
                           </q>
                        </p>
                        <p>Dr. <hi>P. R</hi>'s diſallowing the Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Letters, as being ſo many infamous Libels condemned by his Holineſſe, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the other Treatiſes in the ſame Decree, is a teſtimony of his Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the ſaid Decree, which you and yours will not obey. You call the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33803:19"/>Doctrine thoſe Libels ſtrike at, <hi>Profane and Antichriſtian;</hi> I pray you how Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and Chriſtian is that Caſuiſts Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, who teaches you the ſtraine of this your brave Epiſtle, and to allow of and praiſe an Engliſh Edition of thoſe Libels, bearing in the very Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſpiece an open blaſphemy againſt Gods Saints.</p>
                        <p>As for <hi>Arnauld</hi> you know not what you ſay, nor ſo much as why you ſtile him Doctor; we have heard that after that his Letter excuſing <hi>Janſenius</hi> and the Janſeniſts from Hereſie, was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly condemned in the Sorbon, he was diſgracefully caſhiered the ſaid Sorbon, and had his title of Doctor taken from him in the Yeare 1656. the laſt of January. Do you hear my friend that it was ſince reſtored unto him?</p>
                        <p>You cavil even at a man's ingenuous confeſſion, that when he writ his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, he had not yet ſeen your Maſters <hi>Tabulae Suffragiales.</hi> He hath peruſed them ſince to my knowledge, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve will in due time give your Maſter a good account of them. In the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33803:19"/>I muſt give you this accompt of your great Maſter the Trinobant, in mine own and thoſe many of my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance their names, who have read his Books, that beſides the uſeleſs froth we meet with all along, we finde his pride and ſelf-conceit now grown to ſo high a degree of madneſſe, that we wonder your ſelves do not perceive it, and binde him.</p>
                        <p>But I wonder you ſhould inſert a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your Maſters Praiſes, that you are <hi>ſure Dr. P. R. will never underſtand his Tabulae Suffragiales:</hi> where you make that his glory, which is the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of all good men and writers, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity. Yet that I may not be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either to your or his deſerts: give me leave to tell you, you have in this Paragraph ſumm'd up all that can be ſaid of him in theſe few words. <hi>He is not to be underſtood,</hi> and <hi>he hath extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary and exotick opinions.</hi> The firſt being an effect of the later, a fit cloak for ſuch knavery.</p>
                        <p>But now you ſtrain higher, even above Ela, ſaying, <hi>Mr. White is ſo eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33803:20"/>not to ſay admired, by all the world, for his ſolid and profound learning, and ſo honoured, where he is known, for his piety: who if now and then he have ſome extraordinary and exotick opinions,</hi> &amp;c. For what learning or piety was he ever honoured by any, but onely ſuch whom levity and inconſtancy made to run after every winde of new Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? And I am perſwaded ſcarce any Heretick ever had ſo few follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in ſo long a time that he hath been venting his <hi>Exotick Opinions.</hi> But ſee what opinion the ſound members of the Catholick Church have of him. The Pope hath already condemned many of his writings: and the reſt are like to follow. His own Biſhop hath ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely reprehended him. The ſacred faculty of Divinity of <hi>Doway</hi> have cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured 22. Propoſitions of his for <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall, Erroneous, Dangerous, Temera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, Impious, Scandalous, and Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of pious ears.</hi> Theſe are the Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giums, this the <hi>eſteem, admiration, and honour, all that know him have for him;</hi> who is ſcarce known for any thing but
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33803:20"/>his Hereſies, ſcarce named but with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret and horrour of his novelties.</p>
                        <p>And for <hi>the honour done him where he is known,</hi> 'tis ſo little, that he doth not truſt himſelf in any Catholick Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, as France, Spain, Italy, Belgium, yea, England it ſelf, where his <hi>Exotick Opinions</hi> have bred as great an averſion towards him among moderate Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, as they have begot a deteſtation of him among true Catholicks, who are aſhamed of him, and grieve that the ſon of their mother ſhould fight againſt them.</p>
                        <p>But you continue, and ſay, <hi>If he have ſome extraordinary and Exotick opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, what is that to P. R.?</hi> Why not to him? You would have him ſee a thief, and run with him; betray Hieruſalem to the enemies, upon whoſe gates he ſtood ſentinell: yea then he had been your white Boy, then he might have obtained an eminent place in your <hi>Chapter,</hi> and what not? But now that he hath diſcovered the thief ready to break into the houſe; repulſed the enemy by diſcharging his warning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33803:21"/>
                           <hi>he is a prevaricatour, a miſcreant,</hi> with many other ſuch titles wherewith your uncharitable new Goſpel is ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and bountifully diſpoſeth of to the obedient ſons of the Church.</p>
                        <p>You come at length to the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Chapter,</hi> or capitular government of the Engliſh Cleargy, the very Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the Rump, <hi>Haſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>erig,</hi> in a leſſer Volume; And now Sir, we muſt cry you mercy if we have hitherto thought you a Fool all along: for here you are ſo wiſe as to ſay of the preſent <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Truly I muſt confeſſe, I neither know what it is, nor wherein the validity or invalidity of it may conſiſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I can ſay nothing to it.</hi> Get but your fellows Blackloiſts to confeſſe as much, and we ſhall ſoon agree, and his caball with their unwarrantably uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped juriſdiction ſo ſerviceable to him for the propagation of his Errors, and of ſo dangerous conſequence as to the invalidity of Faculties and Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, will be ſoon defeated by this Confeſſion; and in fine, we ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our obligations to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33803:21"/>you rail at for this ſo neceſſary diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of your preſent Chapter's nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Yet I would not have you miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take Dr. <hi>P. R.</hi> as though he were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Chapter, for I have often heard him wiſh that there were here a competent number of the beſt and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt Cleargy-men impowred by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full authority, with like Juriſdiction to that of Cathedrall Chapters in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Countreys, whereby the whole Cleargy might be governed, whileſt there wanted a Biſhop, and be by way of Counſell to him, when we have one; whether it were called a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or by ſome other fitter name: and that he acknowledged ſome worthy members in this preſent Chapter, to deſerve the ſaid power, however they are now overborn by the more igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and violent party of <hi>Blackloe</hi>'s Faction. And even to theſe I finde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly in his Epiſtle pag. 30. that he is moſt ready to ſubmit himſelf and obey them, if his Holineſſe ſhould think fit to approve of them and confirm them. Where is then that ambition you tax
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33803:22"/>him with, of ſo poor a thing as to be one of this Chapter, eſpecially in the inconſiderable and pitifull condition it is now in?</p>
                        <p>But here again I finde you play the fool by your venturing to play the Stateſman forſooth, when you ſay, You <hi>leave it to the State to conſider, how much it concerns them, not to ſuffer the Catholicks of</hi> England <hi>to be daily run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to</hi> Rome <hi>for the leaſt buſineſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> that may belong them.</hi> The State hath found long ſince by experience that, of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, they are moſt aſſured of their fidelity and loyalty to their Temporal Monarch, who beſt maintain their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to their Spirituall Head. I have heard that ſome of your Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and no others, were complained of for their petty tamperings with the late Uſurper, Committees, and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers.</p>
                        <p>You charge Dr. <hi>P. R.</hi> with ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing, as you ſay, the dead. Were you but half as honeſt, as your hob-naile Northern phraſe, in your praiſing this dead man, you would acknowledge,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33803:22"/>how ſparingly he is ſpoken of, in the Epiſtle; where nothing is ſaid of him, no not what was already made known of him, even by a notable ſtickler of your own gang, and commonly ſpoken up and down the Town. Onely that paſſage of my Lord of <hi>Chalcedon</hi>'s Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, forbidding him to own his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deanſhip any more, and his continuing ſtill to do it, was neceſſary, the ſubject requiring it, to be taken notice of: and even this had been publiſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Doctor <hi>G. L</hi>'s printed Manifeſt. But ſince I underſtand that ſome of you ſeem not yet ſatisfied, you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps heare more hereafter of that dreadful example Almighty God ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to warn us by in the circumſtances of this man's death, whether for his continued diſobedience to his Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or for his obſtinately maintaining and propagating Janſeniſm and Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loiſme, Almighty God knows.</p>
                        <p>You ſeem next, to know wonders, but that your compaſſion obligeth you to conceal the particulars. Of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you hint at in this place, he hath
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33803:23"/>already fully laid all the ſhame at your own doors: and now again I muſt in his name defie you to ſay the worſt you can of him. Even the pretended calumny reached not to any thing done by him, but to idle words ſpoken of him by a Lay Gentleman, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding hath twice under his hand, and will ſtill if need be upon oath, deny all ſuch words as your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion would charge him with. Now my Simpleton, where are you? the quarel groweth now between you and that Lay Gentleman: he will ſhew his face, when you dare not ſhew yours.</p>
                        <p>As for your idle vapouring of <hi>Cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Footmen,</hi> ſince you <hi>profeſſe you have ſome knowledge in the ordinary paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of the world,</hi> why have you not yet learned, that there is not ſuch a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance betwixt a Knight and a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man eſpecially ſuch a one as you bark at: But the two you would here ſet at further variance, might be eaſily brought yet to a faire attonement by diſcreeter men than you and your Maſter.</p>
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:33803:23"/>
                        <p>Your calumny of Dr. <hi>P. R.</hi> his going about to deceive a Dutch Merchant in the Quinquempois-ſtreet at Paris, is a ſilly Devil that was never yet raiſed till now, that your envy hath driven you to theſe miſerable extremities. You ſay the Knight had no hand in it. I believe ſo too, and ſo doth the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, who ſaith, it is too ſimple and too ignoble a revenge for ſuch a perſon to own. Yet I muſt in a word ſtop your mouth in this alſo. The Bill, you have heard ſomething of, was a true Bill of Exchange; the Engliſh Merchant who ſent it, is now in <hi>London,</hi> and will avow it. A noble perſon who appeared in it, and is now alſo in <hi>London,</hi> will ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie to your betters, that there was no cheat done or intended, but a great work of Juſtice and Charity. Yea part of that money was afterwards received by another Bill from the ſame Engliſh Merchant, and diſpoſed of as was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. There's enough for you my Youngſter. Yet I muſt put you in mind that we know of later years, worſe accompt, or rather none at all, given
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33803:24"/>by ſome of your pretended Chapter and Blackloiſts, of far greater ſummes of money, to the ſcandall of the Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, both Catholicks and Proteſtants.</p>
                        <p>But now</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>You ſing</hi> Bellona's <hi>Battles, and the man's whoſe glorious deeds out-did great</hi> Tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlan's. We hear of nothing but <hi>army againſt army, ſingle combats, Don Quix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots, Windmills, Souldiers, Captains, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in the air, with Thraſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>icall boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and bragging,</hi> and ſuch like terrible buggan boes, which have frighted the poor Ideot out of his wits, eſpecially ſince that dreadfull apparition of the formidable inchaunted Giant <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metham,</hi>
                           <q>Monſtrum horrendum, infòrme, ingens, &amp;c.</q>
                        </p>
                        <p>deſcended no doubt of the <hi>renowned and very ancient families of the Dorober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Gogmagogs, and Trinobantian Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bii of the Eaſt-Saxons:</hi> of which race one <hi>Thomas the Engliſhman</hi> (the true parallel of <hi>Don Quixot,</hi> as your ſelf of <hi>Sancho Pancha</hi> his Eſquire) begat him (as the <hi>Cyclops</hi>) of ſome windie phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toſme,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33803:24"/>that ſupplied the place of brain in his empty Pericranium, where, ô the ſtrong force of imagination fertile to its own ruine! in ſmall time it gained ſuch ſtrength, that it is grown terrible to its own parent, whom neither his <hi>Golden Shield</hi> can defend; nor the <hi>Sound</hi> of his <hi>Trumpet</hi> can drive away: nor <hi>Fourteen Animadverſions</hi> joyned to <hi>Sixty ſix Excantations</hi> diſſolve the inchantment. But he layes ſo furiouſly about him on the <hi>Don</hi> and your ſelf his Eſquire, that there is no hope of either of your recoveries, but by <hi>the Balſome of Fierebras;</hi> more commonly known at the <hi>Anticyra's</hi> by the name of <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore:</hi> whither I am reſolved to ſend you both to find your cure. And while the Curate and the Barber are prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a Cart to carry the <hi>Don:</hi> I will take charge of you 'Squire <hi>Sancho:</hi> and when I have made an end with your Libell, ſend you after.</p>
                        <p>And now Sir, you ſee with what pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience I have followed you all along to the end of this your rare piece, where to ſave both your great <hi>Trinobant</hi> and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33803:25"/>your wiſe Doctor with their adherents their credits, for their not dariug in almoſt a year and a halfs time, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer a modeſt challenge offered them in the name of ſome of their Oxtho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Brethren of the Cleargy, where they might upon friendly tearms have received ſuch verball ſatisfaction, as might have prevented the ſcandall of ſuch ſcurrillous and unchriſtian wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting as you and they uſe; you bravely out of an Ivy-buſh ſleight your Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenger, who waits for you in open field, and tell him <hi>that he never put his noſe into a Divinity-School;</hi> wherein you out-do your very Maſters, who have made ſuch triall of his Divinity, that they believe you lye. And I with others do upon enquiry believe, that he hath many years given extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry publick teſtimony of his high abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties therein, in thoſe Divinity-Schools where perhaps your Maſter's noſes would have gone out of joynr, and they have found him ſtill able to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their Novelties to their noſes. You boaſt of your Doctors Learning
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33803:25"/>being known in thoſe famous Schools and Countreys where he lives, and I have heard a perſon of Honour who lived ſome years at <hi>Paris,</hi> and was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the beſt and learned'ſt company, wonder that your Doctor was ſo little known and conſidered, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo many years ſpent in the very place where he lives. I will not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you here with what I have heard others relate of the eſteem the Sorbon Doctors and other Divinity Doctors with whom Dr. <hi>P. R.</hi> lived in commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and miſſions, made of his learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed reſolutions upon ſeverall occurrent Controverſies and Caſes. I know your envy, if I ſhould tell it you, will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly digeſt the credit he was in with that Reverend and learned Officiall of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Toul,</hi> ever ſince in his preſence he put the famous Janſeniſt <hi>De St. Boeuf</hi> Dr. and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of Divinity in Sorbon, at that time under-officiall, to a <hi>non plus,</hi> in a debate concerning a Diſpenſation for a Marriage. It will make you burſt to hear that the moſt illuſtrious and moſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33803:26"/>learned Primate of <hi>Normandy</hi> was heard often to call this worthy Doctor <hi>le tout-ſcavant,</hi> and that ſome very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Noble perſons on this ſide the water, have often reflected with what facility and clearneſs he reſolved them ſtill in what difficulty ſoever they asked him. And all this hath no more puffed him with any part of that va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity your great Maſter is grown mad with, then your ſcurrility is able to leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen his eſteem with thoſe that know him; and for thoſe who know him not, if they believe your Libell, no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man will deſire to know them. Adieu, and learn more wit.</p>
                        <closer/>
                        <postscript>
                           <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
                           <opener>
                              <salute>SIR</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>You date your Letter in 1659. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as your <hi>Maſters Excantation</hi> from whence you borrow your ſtuffe, was not printed before this year 1660. Let me for the better dating of your Letters this next year, recommend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you <hi>Montelion's Almanack,</hi> you
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33803:26"/>will finde your own Picture in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of it; and at the end amongſt the Books newly printed, your Maſters Work under the Title of
<q>
                                 <l>Camera locanda in Purgatorio Odilonis.</l>
                                 <l>Authore Thomas Anglo. A Romance.</l>
                              </q>
                           </p>
                           <p>This Almanack is ſold at the Prince's Armes in Chancery-Lane.</p>
                        </postscript>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Honoured Sir,</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee how I have anatomized this pittifull Owl, which proves nothing but a heap of Feathers, a meer aerie light ſubſtance, diſowned by the Publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſcorned by the Stationer, and even a ſhame to the Author himſelf, who durſt put neither his Name, nor place of his abode, to it. And thus much I thought fit to ſend open to you, that you may read it and then give it the Libeller, if you diſcover him: he hath the mark of the Beaſt, <hi>Since,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>he is not learned in any thing;</hi> he may perhaps prove ſome ignorant Lay Scribler, and your ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Lay man too, there will be no irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33803:27"/>in cudgelling him; Yet by doing ſo you may fail againſt Charity, which indeed will be the greateſt irregularity. And therefore if at the reading hereof he acknowledgeth not the uglineſſe of his guilt, and repent, you may pray for him, and for.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your humble and faithful Servant, T. R.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> Shrewsbury, <date>
                     <hi>on the Feaſt of the immaculate Conception of our B. Lady.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33803:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
